Why does actually shipping our apps
always end up taking longer than we
think it should? It's because every time
we want to focus on building that next
big feature in our road map, we're
ambushed by our backlog. The bug fixes,
the quick requests, or the endless just
one more thing. Well, that changes
today. Enter background agents. This
past month, Cursor just launched their
background agents feature, and OpenAI
launched their codeex product. And both
of these tools are aimed at letting us
offload certain tasks to background
agents so that we can focus our time and
our mental cycles on the more important
things in our road map. So in this
video, I'll show you how I spin up
background agents in cursor and how to
be selective about which jobs are best
for background agents to handle for us.
Look, I'm not here for the hype. After
20 years of writing full stack code by
hand, today I'm building with AI for the
leverage. I want to ship more ambitious
software faster and I want to erase all
the busy work that often makes my craft
feel like a grind. Background agents
feel like the multiplier that we've been
waiting for. Now, in my last video on
this channel, I showed you a new
workflow that professionals are using to
take an active approach to working with
AI agents on largecale projects. In this
video, we're gaining efficiency in our
backlog by delegating those tasks to
background agents. By the way, I'll be
teaching a workshop soon, so drop a
comment below with your top question
about building with AI and I'll make
sure you get in on that. All right,
let's get into it. So, here is an app
that I just built yesterday. It's a
habit tracker app. It's built with Ruby
on Rails and Inertia and React. I built
it in cursor with agent mode. Pretty
simple. It's not quite ready for prime
time yet, but it's coming along. And so
up here, I can track my 14-day streak of
how I'm doing on my habits. Of course, I
have a zero day streak right now because
I just built this app yesterday. And
then I can create these habits down here
that I want to track and I can mark them
off as complete every day and keep the
streak going. Now, I want to speed up my
road map and push some of my backlog to
background agents. So, how should we
think about this? Well, I'm looking for
tasks that I don't want to babysit. I
want them to get done, but while they're
getting done, I need to be working on
something else. Now, I've been testing
background agents this week, and I'm
realizing that there's a pitfall that we
should try to avoid. You know, the
tendency is to want to delegate the
larger, more complex tasks to background
agents because they're so timeconuming.
But while a background agent can execute
most tasks the same way that a
foreground agent can, the more complex
the task is, the more likely it's not
going to be 100% perfect in one shot. So
then you'll probably need to take your
tasks back to your foreground agent,
give it some feedback and tweaks and
finish it off. And that's possible using
cursor's background agents feature and
I'll show you that here. But it sort of
defeats the purpose of delegating to the
background agent in the first place.
Right? So my advice here might seem a
little counterintuitive. But when it
comes to picking tasks to give to your
background agent, I think you should
pick the ones that are easier, smaller,
more predictable because even though you
could knock those out pretty quickly,
they really add up and you should be
focusing your time on the bigger, more
important pieces in your road map. And
by delegating the easier tasks that a
background agent can crush in one shot,
that's how you start to see the
efficiency gains. All right. So, in this
project, here are three chores that I'm
am glad to have a background agent
tackle for me. The first is going to be
a simple design tweak. You see this mark
complete button? I don't really like how
it doesn't really look like a button. It
looks more like an alert or something.
So, we need to make that a more solid
button. And also, I don't like how the
text is to the left. It should be
centered. So, we'll get that cleaned up.
I also noticed a bug. So, if I try to
delete a habit, we're running into this
error. So, we'll let the background
agent handle that. And the last one is
an accessibility task. So currently, if
my system was in dark mode, the app does
not display in dark mode. And so we
should add that dark mode support. So
let me show you how I'm setting up these
background agents in cursor. Now the
first thing is you need to make sure
that you have privacy mode turned off in
cursor. So you'll go to settings and
under general, you've got privacy mode.
That needs to be disabled in order to
use the background agents feature. I
don't know if it'll always be that way
in the future, but currently it is. So,
just make sure you have that disabled.
Another thing, and this gets into the
costs of running background agents in
your cursor account, you do need to make
sure that you have usage based spending
turned on and you'll need to fund it
with $10 or $20 at least. And I really
hope that they change this as the
feature comes out of beta because even
if you haven't used up all of your
included requests, the background agents
are always going to use your usagebased
spending. And if the background agents
are using max mode, which cursor
encourages you to do, each request might
use 10, 25 cents. I've seen some use up
about 50 cents. As you can see, I've
I've been using it a lot this past week.
Now, the bottom line here is I don't
think that using background agents is
cost prohibitive in most cases, but it
is a bit pricier than using a normal AI
agent. So that's another reason why you
want to be more selective with the types
of tasks that you delegate to your
background agent versus the ones that
you handle in your foreground agent.
Okay, let's set up our first background
agent. So in cursor, you can get to your
background agents a few different ways.
You can click this icon up here or I
prefer the keyboard shortcut that's
commande and that'll launch this here.
So this is where you can, you know,
create a background agent or I can
escape out of that and I can also start
a background agent using the main chat
window. By default, it's on agent mode,
but I can switch that to background. And
then it's like the same thing. I'm
creating a background agent here. One
thing you'll notice is it'll
automatically switch the model to a
model that uses max mode. So again, that
does use up more credits than the
non-max models. So, you know, pricing is
something to keep in mind. When I was
using this earlier, it actually didn't
even let me use a non-max model. But
now, I actually can switch it, but
they're still just going to like
recommend that we use a max model. I
think that's because they're assuming
that a background agent needs a really
large context to complete a large task.
Again, my recommendation is to keep the
tasks tight and simple. So maybe a max
mode isn't always required, but you
know, you'll need to experiment with it
and see what works for you. So same
thing over here, you can select the
model. Now, another thing that tripped
me up a few times is you do need to be
aware of which branch you're working off
of. It's always going to default to your
main branch, even if you were previously
working in a different branch. So, if I
was on another feature branch and
there's a bug on this feature, but it's
not actually in the main branch yet,
then I would need to make sure that I
switch to that branch here, so that when
the background agent starts up, it
starts off of that branch. Now, it will
create its own branch to make the change
and then we'll see the PR that we can
merge back in. But here, you do need to
set the branch that you want as your
starting point. This is just a demo app.
I only have the main branch, so we'll go
with that for now. All right, let's get
that first prompt in. You know, again,
I'm just asking it to tweak the design
of the mark complete button so that the
button is more of a solid green color, a
bit larger, and the button text is
centered in the button. All right, so
the first time you do this, it'll ask
you to connect your background agent to
the GitHub repository for this project.
I'm going to click connect. That's going
to take me over to GitHub. You'll need
to make sure that you're adding the
repository. I'll save that. I can close
that. And there we go. That should just
start right up. Now, if you run into
GitHub connection issues, and I have ran
into a few while I was testing this,
you'll need to go into cursor settings,
and you can go to background agents, and
under here, you'll see GitHub access.
You might need to refresh it, reconnect
it. Another thing that I found is
restarting cursor also helps because I
know that cursor caches a lot of these
settings. So, if you change things up on
your GitHub repository, you'll need to
restart. Anyway, that's where you can
troubleshoot things. But looks like we
have our first background agent up and
running. It created a new environment
and then it actually creates like an
interface that essentially is like
another cursor inside of cursor, right?
And so here we go. The background agent
is doing its thing in the chat window
here. I don't need to do anything. I can
just get out of this and I can work on
something else now, right? And actually,
I'm going to let that work and we're
going to start up another background
agent. So, let's take care of that bug
with the delete button. I'm just going
to recreate that error. So, I'm going to
hit delete and we run into the error
there. So, now we have the error in our
logs and I'm just going to highlight
that. Now, I can add to the chat, right?
So, now we have that in the context
window. And instead of just asking the
agent to fix this bug, I'm going to push
it to the background agent. Just like
that. Please fix. We can delete a habit.
All right. So let's open this up again.
And so this is the second background
environment that's being spun up by the
background agent. Now up here we can see
my two tabs, right? So now I have two
different background tasks that are set
up here. This one is just getting
underway. This one is actually showing
the green check mark which means it's
all done. We're going to come back to
that. We're going to look at the results
in just a minute. But first I want to
add a third background agent. And again
that third one was to implement dark
mode for our app. So, I'm going to start
up another background agent. I'm going
to give it this prompt where I'm asking
it to support dark mode so that when a
user's system is set to dark mode, all
of our colors in the app will show the
dark versions that are in the app. I'm
also telling it like, hey, we don't yet
need to implement a toggle switch for
light and dark mode. That's something
that I can add later and maybe consider
giving it to another background agent.
But again, my goal is to keep these
tasks tight and simple and easy to
complete in one shot. So, let's go ahead
with this one. And we're spinning up our
third background agent. And so, now I
can toggle between my three different
background agent jobs. And the first two
now show that they've been completed and
the dark mode task is doing its thing.
So, again, while that works, I'm going
to go take a walk, maybe grab a coffee,
do some other work, might even do some
marketing work for a change. Okay. Okay.
Now, while the dark mode task is still
working, let's take a look to see how we
did on the other two tasks since they
both seem to be done now. So, let's go
to that first one where we tweaked the
design of the mark complete button. So,
when it's all set, you'll see the green
check mark and I can, you know, go back
and review all the history from this
background agent. I can review the file
changes. This was a pretty simple one.
Looks like just one line change here
with a bunch of new tailwind styling. So
over here we have a couple options. I
can create a pull request which I'm
going to do in a minute. But first I
actually want to check it out locally so
that I can take a look. Right. So I'm
going to click this. And what this does
is it actually checks out the branch
that cursor created. So my terminal is
set up to show me which branch I'm
currently on. And I can see that I'm on
this branch. So cursor creates a new
branch named cursor slash the name of
the task. And that's where it does all
of its work. So it's separate from, you
know, whatever other code you have going
on in your project. So now that I have
it checked out locally, I can run my
server and take a look to see how it
did. Okay, so this is actually much
better. I can see the mark complete
button. It actually looks like a button
now. The text is centered and yeah,
that's working well. I'm going to
complete this habit because I actually
did do my exercise this morning. All
right, so I've got a little little bit
of a streak here. It's getting a little
choppy, but that's okay. All right,
let's see how we're doing on the other
tasks. So, our dark mode task is still
in progress, but the fix for deleting
habits appears to be all set. So, here
it is. I can again review the code.
Looks like a simple fix here. I've got
the summary from the agent and I am
going to check it out locally so that I
can test it out to make sure that it
works. So, I'll click that. Okay, so now
we're on that branch and I'm going to
start my server. I can sort of take a
look and see what happened here. I can
look at the file itself and I can see
the changes. It was a simple fix. So,
I'm going to refresh and let's try to
delete a habit. There we go. It works.
Good to go. Now, before we check the
work on implementing dark mode, the next
step after you've taken a look at the
results of your background agents work
is you can create a pull request. So,
I'll close this. So once you see the
green check mark, you'll have this
ability to create a pull request and
that'll open up GitHub. It'll write up a
whole pull request with all the details.
You can go ahead and create that and
then you or someone on your team or
maybe another AI agent can actually
review the code and then merge it into
your project when you're ready. So now
I'm in the other background task for
improving the mark complete button. That
one needs a pull request. So I'll go
ahead and click that. And here it is. It
wrote it up with all the details. Very
cool. So that's all set to go and we can
merge that in a little bit later. All
right. Finally, let's go into our dark
mode implementation. And our AI has
given us sort of a summary. It made a
bunch of changes. So this one actually
made quite a few changes to multiple
files and it added, you know, all the
dark variants to all the tail and CSS
colors. So let's take a look at that.
I have checked out that branch. I'm
going to refresh my server. This
probably isn't even necessary. It's just
sort of a habit, especially when I'm
making like a CSS changes. So, I'm going
to refresh now. I'm going to set my
system to dark mode. And hey, there we
go. So, we're in dark mode. Nice. It
actually did a pretty good job of
finding every single color on the page
and giving it like a dark mode variant.
Now, I'll probably want to tweak this
hover state. That looks a little bit
weird, but you know, I can get to that a
little bit later. Maybe in a separate
task, maybe even for a background agent.
So, that works. I'm going to go ahead
and create that pull request. There it
is. Add dark mode support. Got all the
details. I'll create the pull request.
And then when our app is ready for each
of these fixes or new features to be
merged in, we just need to go into the
pull request and merge it up. All right.
I've got a challenge for you. I want you
to think about your current project that
you're working on this week. pick out
one task that you would like to delegate
to a background agent and then leave a
comment and tell us what your project is
and what that task is. I want us to like
create a big list of task ideas that we
can all start to think about as things
that we can get off of our plates,
delegate them to background agents, and
we can become more productive. Now, when
you want to take a more active approach
to leveraging AI in your big important
projects, you'll need a better approach
than just vibe coding and spinning your
wheels. So, check out my other video
where I show you how professionals are
building with AI right now. See you
there.